- Previously on Gotham...
- Gotham falls, we rise.
GORDON: After the bridges blew,
the city was up for grabs.
Gangs are carving up territory.
(screams)
We are running out of food.
(shouting)
Ammunition.
We are surrounded
by hostile forces.
Say hello to Butch.
(screams)
Put out the word.
100,000 rounds of ammunition
to whoever kills Jim Gordon.
(siren wails)
NURSE: You want to cure her?
(whispering): You
have to go to the witch.
And where do I find this witch?
You have to help us.
My brothers and sisters,
they're killing us.
GORDON: His name is Will Thomas.
Parents died in a home invasion
a few weeks after the
bridges came down.
Guys that broke in
took him to some sort of factory
where he was held alongside
dozens of other stolen kids,
all chained together.
BULLOCK: God.
Who are these guys?
Call themselves The Soothsayers.
- You ever heard of them?
- No.
But who can keep
track these days?
- Which district?
- Granton. Near the water,
he said. Had them
digging some sort of tunnel.
Will broke free from
his restraints last night
and walked nine miles
through the Dark Zone to find us.
What kind of tunnel?
Unclear.
There's an abandoned waterworks
by the old dock in Granton.
Detective Gordon?
My friends.
You'll save them, won't you?
I'll look into it.
The Soothsayers won't
be happy I escaped.
They'll punish
the others for it.
Please, Mr. Gordon.
I promised them I'd bring help.
I know it's a sad story
and emotions are high,
but need I remind you that
every two-bit criminal out there
is looking to kill you to
claim Penguin's bounty?
So you're saying we do nothing?
No, I'm saying the second
you step outside that door,
someone's gonna
take a shot at you,
and if it's not you
that's getting hit,
it's gonna be the schmo
standing next to you,
which is most
likely gonna be me.
Captain.
There's a call
from the mainland.
MAN: All of us here believe
that if peace is to be
sustained on the island,
confrontations must be avoided.
We have kids in
danger out there.
We're their only
hope for rescue.
MAN: Your dedication to
your job is admirable, Captain,
but you lack perspective.
Travel into harm's way,
and you may save a few lives,
but you'd also be jeopardizing
thousands of others
should you be killed.
The collective opinion over
here is that you stand down
and keep those within
your Green Zone safe.
I don't need opinions,
I need supplies.
When can I expect them?
MAN: Until Gotham airspace
can be declared safe again,
we cannot sacrifice
any more pilots,
whether they're ours
or Wayne Enterprises'.
So you can save a few lives
for thousands, but I can't?
MAN: Mr. Gordon...
BULLOCK: Jim.
I need five men and
transport for 20 kids or more.
We only have a few squad cars
- and that rust bucket
transporter.
- That'll have to do.
How are we on ammo?
Well, we got what
we got from Penguin,
and we got a box
of shotgun shells
and a box of nine mils.
What did the bureaucrats
on the mainland say?
Do nothing, protect
the Green Zone.
Four shells each.
Half a mag each.
Boy said The
Soothsayers are here.
That means we have to
pass through Sirens territory,
but it's only three or
four miles from then on.
Three or four miles
into the Dark Zone?
God only knows what's out there.
Barbara's been
stockpiling vehicles
and everything else as
payment to enter her club.
- It's worth a shot.
- She's gonna be thrilled
to see you after what
happened with Tabitha.
We're gonna need housing
for those kids when we get back.
- Yep.
- If we get back.
(dog barking in distance)
(gate creaks)
(insects trilling)
♪♪
(water dripping)
(footsteps approaching)
(panting)
MAN: Let him go.
- Are you with her?
- Who?
The witch.
I'm not with the witch.
I just came here for her help.
Come for her magic, have you?
So did others from our district.
And look at them now.
They came for help, too,
and she took their souls.
But she'll never kill again.
We have her this time.
You captured her?
She's locked in the
storeroom back there.
We stripped it clean
before we locked her in.
The plants, you see.
She talks to them.
Makes them do things.
So we took her light,
water; put salt on the floor.
She's helpless now.
I need to talk to her.
No. We sent
for more of us.
When they come, we burn her.
Listen.
My brother is missing.
I know this witch took him.
I need to find out
what she did with him.
Please, let me talk to her.
Five minutes is all I need,
and then you can do
whatever you want.
Your brother's dead.
She'll kill you, too.
Five minutes.
In there.
Hello, Ivy.
♪♪
♪ Love is a burning thing ♪
♪ And it makes ♪
♪ A fiery ring ♪
♪ Bound by wild desire ♪
♪ I fell into a ring of fire ♪
♪ I fell into... ♪
Barbara.
This place is busy,
despite things.
What's that?
♪ And the flames went higher ♪
It's a big fat prize, Jim,
begging to be taken.
So, what brings you crawling
out into the open tonight?
Come to join the party?
One last hoorah before
someone wastes you?
I'm here to ask a favor.
(laughs)
A favor, right. Is this after
you stood by and did nothing
while my best
friend on this Earth
was stabbed through the heart?
- I put him down.
- You restored his limp.
- He should be dead!
- Barbara.
Everybody out!
- Now!
- (music stops)
I said move!
Planning revenge?
Well, someone has to do
something about that freak.
He has an army.
It would be suicide.
Look around, Jim.
We're all slowly dying.
Just some of us
get to choose how.
I'm sorry about what
happened to Tabitha.
Things got out of control.
I'm just trying to keep
this city from falling apart.
You're too late.
So, this favor?
I need transportation.
- Trucks, maybe.
- Where are you going?
- It's a police matter.
- (laughs softly)
You know, they should really
write that on your tombstone.
(chuckles)
They're downstairs
in the basement lot.
Knock yourself out.
Drive right into this
nightmare you created.
You won't last the night.
Here he comes, Gotham.
Your judge, your jailer,
your most hated son!
Have at him!
Rip him to shreds!
(door closes)
No one deserves
to die more than he.
BULLOCK: All right, we're
entering the Dark Zone.
Everybody, stay sharp.
This place was a cesspit
before the rest of the
world turned its back on us.
I wonder what's left here now.
I doubt many stayed up here.
This whole grid
never regained power.
(glass breaking)
(shouting)
Damn it! You were saying, Jim?
(shouts)
It's a freaking arrow, Jim.
It's a freaking arrow!
Welcome to the badlands.
(grunts) Come on.
- Come on, come on.
- (groans softly)
- Get up!
- Aah!
Come on!
Hey! Hey, hey, hey.
Leave him alone.
Causing trouble again, Gabriel?
We need water and food.
Some of us haven't slept
in two days.
You know, you could've woken me
when that sneaky
rat left in the night.
But you didn't, and
now, he's out there,
and he's causing all
kinds of problems for us.
(exhales) The smoke.
You should take it.
It'll give you energy.
Inhale enough...
and it'll let you
see the future.
You fail to see the importance
of our work here, Gabriel.
But you see, once
this tunnel is complete,
we will have exclusive
access to the mainland.
People will be forced
to do business with us.
Food, booze, guns,
smoke.
All will come from the tunnel.
We've been digging
for over a month.
We've only gotten
a hundred feet.
It's too narrow.
The roof is leaking. Once
we hit the river, it'll flood
- and kill anyone inside.
- So negative!
Gabriel.
Shame.
I had such high hopes for you.
That one day you would
wear the mask and share
in our good fortune.
Never mind.
MAN: Sykes.
Man, you got to come out front.
Who was on watch?!
GORDON: Put your weapons down.
Is that James Gordon?
The James Gordon?
It's our lucky day, fellas.
Kill this one, and
we're bullet rich!
In Penguin's graces we will be.
(guns clicking)
I said put 'em down.
Give us the kids
you're holding
captive. We'll leave.
Kids?
I don't know what
you're talking about.
What are the cattle prods for?
Fun.
Stay here.
He moves, kill him.
It's okay.
It's all right. I'm a cop.
Will's alive?
He found you and sent
you to rescue us, didn't he?
He did.
Will made it! He's alive!
- (cheering)
- We need the keys.
There are trucks outside.
We'll drive you to
the Green Zone,
find you a new home.
Thank you. God bless you.
Okay, guys. We're
gonna get out of here.
Gonna help us get
out. One at a time.
Yeah, we're gonna be okay.
Why would anyone be
a cop in a world like this?
Well, the Halloween shop
was all out of gas masks,
so it was either
this or sexy nurse.
You know what?
My guess is these cops ain't
got enough ammo to shoot a duck.
Wrong. Penguin
gave us a boatload.
Penguin wants your boss skinned.
Let's take 'em, boys.
Come on! Go! Go!
(gunfire)
(Bullock yells)
(gunfire continues)
Hey!
Go!
(child screams)
Gabriel!
You okay? Come on.
- Take cover! Go! Go!
- (whimpers)
- The alley! Go! Go!
- Come on!
(yelling)
(gasps softly)
Bruce?
(sighs)
Thank God.
You have to help me.
I didn't kill those men
out there in the vines,
- you have to believe me.
- You'll forgive me
if I find it hard to do so.
It wasn't me.
It was the park.
The park?
The trees, the plants, the roots
underground...
They're speaking to one another.
When those men
came to kill me...
(panting)
the plants came
to my protection.
Then maybe we
can help each other.
I have...
a friend... who was shot.
The bullet severed
her spinal cord.
The doctors can't
seem to help her.
But a woman at the hospital
said that you might be able to.
Normally, I would say no.
But this park... ever
since we were cut off
from the rest of the world,
it's been behaving differently.
There are things growing here
I have never seen before.
- (knocking)
- MAN:
You okay in there?
Our friends are on their way.
Time's running
out for you, witch!
There's a seed.
It's growing under the oaks.
It's said to have
magical qualities.
When digested, it heads
for damaged tissue
and bone, healing them.
If I help you find it...
will you protect me from
those men out there?
(gasps)
(chains rattle)
Yes! Yes!
Yes, it worked!
No... more...
sleepwalking for me.
(sighs)
Good morning.
(zipper opens)
(sighs)
See, it was just some...
random stupid thing
brought on by stress.
(urinating)
It's all in your head.
(man groaning)
There's nothing there.
(laughs)
(sighs)
(man groaning)
(zipper closes)
- (gasps)
- Who the hell are you?
What? Are you serious?
Very.
You don't remember?
- No.
- Oh.
Name's Tank.
You're part of the
Street Demonz gang?
Yeah.
You know that.
Why should I?
What are you doing here?
You brought me here.
- I brought you here?
- Last night.
Did I, uh...
hit you, et cetera?
Any idea why?
You wanted information,
and I wouldn't give it to you.
I'm gonna guess
you gave it to me.
Huh. I can't remember.
We're gonna have to do
this all again, aren't we?
Guess so.
Fine.
SYKES: Gordon, where are you?
We need to hide.
Follow me.
(door creaks closed)
It's not safe out there.
We've got to get
out of the daylight.
We're sitting ducks.
How are they holding up?
We'll be fine.
Jim, we're not alone.
Someone lit that candle.
In the old west, settlers
used to leave a candle burning
to lead others to safety.
Maybe there's still good
people left in Gotham.
All right, fine.
We'll take a look around.
Stay here.
If you see something, shout.
Radio check.
Ah, forget it.
We're out of range of
the precinct's antenna.
Look, if those other trucks
made it back to safety,
maybe they'll send someone
back here to get us, huh?
Maybe. Until then, I'll take the
next floor, you do the basement.
Oh. Check out the basement
in a creepy hotel by myself?
Sure.
What could go wrong, right?
(sighs)
Let's get settled.
(floorboards creaking)
(door creaks)
(creaking nearby)
Hello?
Is somebody there?
GCPD.
Come out, now.
Whoa, whoa. It's
okay. It's all right.
(fire crackling)
♪♪
Oh, my God.
Oh. Not good.
Oh, God. This...
This is not good.
(shouts) Jim!
(grunts, groans)
Fine. I'll tell you.
You wanted to know where
the Street Demonz base was.
That's it?
And you wanted to be sure
the boss would be there.
Emmanuel Vasquez?
Yeah.
Okay. How did I seem?
Was I confident, flamboyant,
charisma for days?
Or a little more conservative,
kind of repressed,
a little nerdy?
You seemed stiff,
man of few words.
In a daze, actually.
Interesting.
Okay, let's go.
Where?
To where you told me to go.
To the Street Demonz' base.
To Vasquez.
I want to know why I went there.
- Oh, no!
- Push her back inside. Lock the door.
Stay calm.
Okay? Her name is Ivy.
She's a witch,
and will burn for
what she's done.
I take full
responsibility for her.
If she's done what you say,
she will pay for
her crimes, but...
You are so utterly naive.
You didn't have to kill them.
I wanted to.
Why are you here?
I'm here for my friend.
Our friend.
Selina.
Selina's the one that's hurt?
She's paralyzed and
has lost the will to live.
Good.
That bitch destroyed the
last of the Lazarus Water.
Let her suffer.
I don't believe you mean that.
You've known each
other for a long time.
You grew up on
the streets together.
You know, I wasn't lying when
I said this park is changing.
I'm feeding the earth with
these wretched creatures.
It consumes them,
and then it flourishes.
I think I shall plant
your body in the ground, Bruce.
What will grow
from you, I wonder?
Those men you killed were right.
You are a witch.
A murderous, callous witch.
Trying to bait me, boy?
I wouldn't waste my breath.
I can see there's
no good left in you.
If you were trying to
help this park flourish,
it would be full of
beauty and color.
Instead it smells of death.
It's a work in progress.
It's a nightmare.
If I do help you,
you'll leave me alone?
Follow me.
It's okay.
I'm Jim. What's your name?
I-I can't remember.
Where are your parents?
Dead.
When the lights
went out in the city,
a gang came, they murdered them.
I ran.
She found me.
Who?
The ghost.
She was kind at first.
But she can be very cruel.
BULLOCK: Jim!
We're not alone.
There's a crazy woman.
She's killing people.
The ghost. We got to go.
- She hates strangers.
- There's no such thing
as ghosts.
We'll protect you
from whoever she is.
You can't.
Why? Who is she?
She makes me call her Mother.
We got to go.
He's not lying! Come on, Jim.
Hey!
Come on!
- Kid!
- (pounding on door)
Hey, kid!
The lights will make you dizzy.
And then you'll fall asleep.
You won't feel a thing.
(groaning)
Jim, I don't feel so good.
(grunts)
(door rattling)
BOY: You can't
fight it. Give in to it.
BULLOCK: Jim!
(grunts)
- Who are you?
- I'm the only mother
that boy knows.
You're a crazy bitch
who kills people,
takes their stuff and
burns their bodies.
I'm protecting him.
When I found him,
he was barely alive.
Those animals out there,
they would have
killed him or worse.
I taught him how to survive.
(both grunting)
Hey!
Where is everybody?
Beats me.
Come on.
Oh, boy.
TANK: Holy crap.
That's Vasquez.
Did you do this?
Honestly, I don't remember.
What about that?
Penguin did this.
I think not.
Well, whoever did just
started one hell of a war.
♪♪
Here.
Is that human blood?
(laughs softly)
If Selina ingests this, it'll
find its way to her wound.
Its roots will wrap
around her spine,
fusing the nerves
and cartilage together.
It'll cure her?
Maybe.
Just maybe?
Everyone's different.
Depends on how strong she is.
One thing is for sure though...
The seed will alter her forever.
- How?
- Some say
the darker angels of our
nature are unlocked and set free.
Can she live with that?
Can you?
I don't know if
there's any other way.
Then go. Give it to her.
What's the matter, Bruce?
Don't know if you can trust me?
- I don't.
- Good.
Then you're finally
becoming a man.
- Where will you go?
- Where I'm going
is none of your business.
Best hurry.
That root will die if left
out in the open for too long.
Uh...
Where have you guys been?
You've been gone for a while.
Chasing ghosts.
They're like rats
in the walls. This
whole place is
their spiderweb. Come
on. Let's go, let's go.
We got to go. Not
everyone wants your help,
Jim Gordon.
Detective Gordon,
your hand's bleeding.
We need to leave.
Come on.
(dog barking in distance)
How many bullets you got left?
Two.
(ignition sputtering)
(engine revving)
SYKES: Looky here, boys!
I'll tell you what,
you give me my workers back,
and I'll let you and
your partner go.
I'm just kidding.
Of course I'm not gonna do that.
I'm gonna kill you all!
WOMAN: Wait just a minute,
please.
The prize for this man's head
is mine.
How is she?
Not great.
I mean, she hasn't said a peep
since you've been gone.
You all right?
Did you find the witch?
It was Ivy.
What's that?
Ivy said it could help Selina.
What, and you trust her?
What choice do I have?
Listen, I want to help
Selina as much as you,
but Ivy is a maniacal,
cold-hearted killer.
- You know that,
don't you?
- Give it to me.
Selina, I have doubts.
Bruce, I was willing
to kill myself yesterday.
Nothing's changed since then.
So if Ivy wants to kill me,
she can have at it.
What do I do, just swallow it?
Yeah.
(sighs)
Still here.
(chuckles)
I know Ivy's lost her mind.
But...
after her mom and dad died,
she was just...
sleeping on the streets.
And it was a cold winter, and...
she started to get really sick.
So I...
took her under my wing, I guess,
and...
showed her where to get food,
where to get a
roof over her head.
And after some time,
she started to get
color in her face.
(chuckles)
And I just...
kept checking in on her.
Almost every day.
She may look old now, but...
she'll always be
that little girl to me.
(shuddering)
- No, no, no, Selina.
- ALFRED: Doctor!
- Selina.
- Doctor!
Selina, stay with me.
- (whimpering)
- Stay back. Give us room.
No, Selina.
DOCTOR: She's burning up.
Pulse is low. What happened?
Oh, God, what have I done?
Put it down, Knucklehead!
You two clowns ain't got a
single bullet between you.
Wrong.
I got two.
Prove it.
I won't say it again, freak.
Gordon comes with me.
I'll tell you what!
I'll take his head,
and you can have
the rest of him!
♪♪
(vehicle approaching)
Hi, Jim.
About our last chat...
I may have been a little rash.
This what got you
all hot and bothered?
- They need a bath.
- Crazy bi...
Wow.
Your last bullet,
just for me, huh?
Must be love.
Not all square yet though.
You're gonna help me do
what we all know needs doing.
Oh, yeah? What's that?
Kill Penguin.
How 'bout we table this
until I can get them safely
into the Green
Zone, huh? Come on.
Wow.
You're safe now. Go on.
LUCIUS: You made it.
You had me worried.
All sorts of chatter out
there about people hunting
you down for Penguin's
reward money.
Well, they'll just
have to try harder.
He did have help from
the unlikeliest of places.
You're welcome.
Show me what you got.
Nice place.
250 apartments. Running
water, hot and cold.
Gas. No electricity yet.
Is there a bar?
LUCIUS: Once the kids
we liberated moved in,
word got out pretty
fast that there was
a safe place to
live in the city.
Citizens are heading
here in droves.
This place will be
full by sundown.
Then we'll find another.
I just want to thank
you, Captain Gordon.
My family, we've been drifting
from one place to the next
ever since the blackout.
You've delivered us.
Seriously?
I'll see you around, killer.
We have some unfinished
business, you and I.
DOCTOR: Whatever she
took put her body into shock.
Her temperature skyrocketed.
Her WBC count
was off the charts.
Then, two hours ago,
everything stabilized.
I have no idea why.
She was still in a lot of
pain, so we sedated her.
She's been sleeping
for a while now.
I think it'd be best to
come back in the morning.
Thank you, Doctor.
Right. Master Bruce,
I think we should,
uh...
we should get some shut-eye.
Come on.
♪♪
Bruce.
It's a miracle.
How do you feel?
(wind blowing)
Different.
Any pain?
No.
Selina, I thought
I'd killed you.
I'm better.
Even better than
before, in fact.